# 今天做啥子菜
What are you cooking today?
# 你看么 皮蛋
As you can see, century eggs
# 做一个烧椒皮蛋
I’m going to make century eggs with charred chillies
# 其实这个烧就是这么玩的 非常简单
That’s how you char the chillies, very easy
# 好吃好看
It looks gorgeous and tastes great
# 我第一步先要烫一点红油
Firstly, I need to make some red chilli oil
# 四川啥子的地方的菜
Where does this dish come from in Sichuan?
# 在成都做的这个菜比较多一点
It’s most commonly seen in Chengdu
# 重庆也在做 内江也在做
You can also find it in Chongqing and Neijiang
# 这个东西都一样
The method is all the same
# 只是他们采用的这个东西
But the ingredients used in this recipe
# 各有千秋不一样
Can be varied in different regions
# 咱们这个用的是线椒
Here, we opt for these long chillies
# 线椒肉比较厚 它会有脆脆的口感
The flesh is comparatively thicker, which will give us the crunchy texture
# 这个是用的二荆条的（辣椒面）
These crushed chillies are made from Erjingtiao chilli peppers
# 差不多油温合适就呲一下
We will sizzle them when the oil temperate is right
# 然后还是一样 加一点凉油
As usual, add some cold oil first
# 简单一些
It makes things simpler
# 我这又放了点凉油
I have added some more cold oil
# 免的辣椒面等会糊了
To prevent the chillies from getting burnt
# 油温烧起来大概差不多六成左右
The oil is about 60 percent hot (180 degree centigrade)
# 先少倒一点进去
Add a little bit in first
# 差不多合适 就把它倒进去
Pour the rest of the oil into the bowl when you feel comfortable
# 然后放一点醋把味道激发出来
Then add some vinegar to bring out the flavour
# 看一下 呲辣椒油搁点醋
Look, sizzling chilli oil with vinegar
# 一个是香
It’s so fragrant
# 让味道释放的更加充分些
And the flavour is being fully released
# 还有一个一会儿这个辣椒
In the meantime, the chilli oil will be able
# 它能扒到菜上
To stick on other ingredients when plating the dish
# 放那儿
Put it there
# 现在我来烧椒
Now, let’s char the chillies
# 辣椒稍微串一下
Skewer these chillies first
# 其实这个烧就是这么玩的
That’s how you char the chillies
# 在农村里面把辣椒直接放在
In the countryside, we normally just put the chillies
# 烧完膛火的炉灰 柴火灰
Directly on the embers from the wood fire oven
# 直接把辣椒扔进去就好了
Just throw them in there until done
# 让它这样烧 烧出虎皮
Char them like this to get the slightly burnt skins
# 它里面同时也熟了
It also cooks the flesh inside at the same time
# 起虎皮了 待会把虎皮去掉 把皮撕掉
The skins are slightly burnt now, which will be removed later
# 其实还有一种方法
There is actually another method
# 也可以在锅里面去焙
That you can toast the chillies in the pan
# 锅里面什么都不放就干的 干焙
Just dry toast them without adding anything else
# 但是它没有这种燎的香
But the chillies wouldn’t be as fragrant as what we are getting here
# 燎的时候它起了虎皮之后
After the skins are slight burnt
# 还是要有点余温 让它稍微熟一点
Keep them warm so they can be properly cooked
# 别到时候辣椒会有点生
In case the flesh is still raw
# 好了 巴适的很
Done! Fantastic!
# 你看现在拿刀稍微把它刮掉
Now roughly remove the skins with a knife
# 不用刮的太干净 刮的时候
You don’t need to remove them completely
# 直接这样我切长一点
Julienne the chillies like this
# 其实手撕也行
You can also rip them apart by hand
# 你看线椒这个香啊 清香嘞
The fragrance of these long chillies is extraordinary. So fresh!
# 这就是比锅里焙的香啊
They are much more fragrant than those toasted in the pan
# 对 就是燎的它比较香一点
Indeed. The charred ones smell so much better
# 准备好了 然后现在就是调汁
They are ready now. Let’s move on to making the sauce
# 这个菜调汁是关键 非常简单
The sauce is key for this dish. It’s very easy to make
# 姜末 大概有个二十克左右
About 20g of minced ginger
# 蒜末也差不多
Same amount of minced garlic
# 香油 来一点点的香油
A touch of sesame oil
# 这个不要太多
Don’t add too much of this
# 然后再来点花椒油
Then some Sichuan pepper oil
# 稍微比香油要多一点
Slightly more than the sesame oil
# 米醋 一勺 一勺半
One and half spoons of rice vinegar
# 酱油 也是一勺半差不多吧
Soy sauce, one and half spoons as well
# 一看就是三合油
The typical Sanheyou (a sauce made from sesame oil, soy sauce and vinegar)
# 然后来点味精
Then, a bit MSG
# 来点盐 盐适量
Some salt, to taste
# 然后放一个刚才烫的最关键的东西哦
And of course, the most essential ingredient we made earlier
# 辣椒油要带底子
The red chilli oil including the chillies in it
# 带点辣椒面
The crushed chillies
# 我觉得酱油还要来一点
I think we need some extra soy sauce
# 不够 这个汁儿很关键
It’s not enough. The sauce is so important
# 好差不多了
Alright, that’s it
# 家庭里面做菜
When you cook at home
# 咱们要漂漂亮亮的 要漂亮
The dish shall be beautifully presented. They must look nice
# 齐活 多棒 这菜快 还好吃呢
All assembled. How good! This is a quick and easy recipe, and it’s delicious
# 把这个烧椒堆在中间
Pile up the charred chillies in the middle
# 这个汁 从中间浇 为了好看
Pour the sauce also from the middle for better presentation
# 都搁里面差不多了
Put most of the sauce there
# 最后那点汁还要淋一圈
Save the last bit to drizzle around the plate
# 要转圈 这样它才有味道
Circle like this, so the sauce is fully incorporated into the dish
# 好吃好看
It looks gorgeous and tastes great
# 放点葱花在上面
Sprinkle some spring onions on the top
# 这个菜安逸了
This dish is now served
# 这回不管大爷了我先尝尝 您必须嘞
I’ll tuck in first before Da Ye this time. Of course, help yourself
# 不会难吃的
It won’t taste bad
# 一定是好吃的很
It must taste amazing
# 他做那汁太香了
The sauce he made is so aromatic
# 小菜 但是做出了浓浓的家乡的味道
It’s a small dish, but it brings out a rich and strong Sichuan flavour
# 烧椒的味 皮蛋的味 汁水的味
The flavours of charred chillies, century eggs and the sauce
# 融在一起 我跟你说
When you combine them together, let me tell you
# 味道浓你看 料汁辣椒 太香了这个
Yes, the flavour is so rich. Look at the sauce and chillies. It’s absolutely brilliant!
# 杨兵下次再搞几个小菜过来
Bring us some more small dishes (appetiser) next time, Yang Bing
# 老菜 家乡菜 带过来几个
Traditional Sichuan local dishes. Just bring them here
# 我爱吃
I simply love them
# 不是你爱吃 是都爱吃
It’s not just you, but we all love them
# 师父爱吃 这个作业就交得好
As long as the master loves it, I consider my job well done
# 这好吃 这真好吃
This is tasty, this is SO tasty!